Well, here we are again in Google Colab.
다시 구글 콜랩에 왔네요
It's been a minute since we were here, and welcome back to it.
여기 온 지 좀 됐는데 잘 돌아왔어요
Uh, this week we're going to spend our time here and it's going to be terrific.
이번 주에는 여기서 시간을 보낼 거예요 정말 멋질 거예요
It's actually it's going to be the best week yet.
최고의 한 주가 될 거예요
I know I keep saying that, but this time it really, really is going to be peak peak.
제가 계속 그렇게 말하지만 이번엔 정말 절정일 거예요
The only thing that's going to be better than what we do here is what's coming next week in week eight,
지금보다 더 나은 건 8주 차에 나올 다음 주 영상뿐이에요
which really, I mean, I can't wait to tell you about that.
빨리 보여드리고 싶네요
But stay focused, keep on week seven.
하지만 7주 차에 집중하세요
There's a lot to go through here.
살펴볼 게 많아요
So first we do.
그럼 먼저 하죠
I've set up this week seven day one Colab.
이번 주에는 콜랍을 7일간 준비했어요
We start with some installs.
설치부터 시작하죠
Um, and one of the things we're installing is a new package you've not seen before, a hugging face
저희가 설치하는 것 중 하나는 여러분이 처음 보시는 새로운 패키지예요
library called Peft, which stands for parameter efficient fine tuning, parameter Efficient Fine Tuning,
얼굴을 끌어안는 Pft라는 라이브러리인데 매개 변수 효율적인 미세 조정의 약자죠 매개 변수 효율
which is their name for the library that includes Laura.
미세 조정 로라를 포함한 라이브러리의 이름이에요
Uh, it's within this library.
이 라이브러리 안에 있어요
Pfft, pfft.
네
Just rolls off the tongue.
입에 착 붙네요
Um, so that is it.
그게 다예요
I am on a T4 box, which is the lowest of the GPU boxes, which just has 15, gigabytes of GPU Ram.
T4 박스에 올라왔습니다 GPU 박스에서 가장 낮은 것으로 15기가바이트의 GPU 램이 있죠
You can see, most of which I'm already using up just a few cells into this.
보시다시피 대부분 이미 셀 몇 개를 사용하고 있죠
So anyway, we do our Pip installs.
어쨌든 우리는 Pip 설치를 해요
We do a bunch of imports here, uh, and set some constants.
수입품도 많이 만들고 상수도 설정했어요
We're going to be working with a base model which is llama 3.18 billion.
기본 모델인 llama 3으로 작업할 거예요 180억 달러요
And I'm also setting a fine tuned model here.
미세 튜닝 모델도 설정하고 있어요
I obviously we haven't done any fine tuning yet.
아직 세부 조정은 안 했어요
I'm.
네
This is from the future.
미래에서 온 거예요
Uh, I'm bringing this in just so I can show you what a fine tuning model looks like in terms of the
이걸 가져와서 미세한 조율 모델이 어떤지 보여 드릴게요
the the Laura matrices applying to the target modules.
로라 행렬이 목표물 모듈에 적용되는 걸 보면요
And then here are three hyper parameters which now you're an expert on are which I am setting to 32.
여기 3개의 하이퍼 매개 변수가 있어요 이제 당신이 전문가니까 32로 설정할게요
You probably remember I said start with eight and then go to 16 and then go to 32.
8로 시작해서 16으로 가고 32로 가라고 한 거 기억하죠?
Well I got to 32.
32,000달러까지 올렸어요
Uh, and that was where I ended up.
그렇게 된 거예요
Uh, and so I'm doing 32 here.
전 지금 32마일로 가고 있어요
Uh, alpha is a rule of thumb, double R.
알파는 경험에서 나온 거예요
So there it is at 64.
64에 있네요
And the target modules.
목표 모듈도요
So these are the four names of the layers that we are targeting.
이건 우리가 대상으로 하는 레이어 이름 4개예요
And you will see why shortly.
그 이유는 곧 알게 될 거예요
And this is by far the most common, uh, setup for llama models.
이게 가장 흔한 라마 모델이에요
Other models may have different names of their layers, but yeah, you give the names of the layers
다른 모델은 계층 이름이 다를 수도 있지만 네, 여러분이 대상으로 할
that you will be targeting in this list that you assign to target modules.
이 리스트에서 대상으로 할 계층 이름을 부여하죠 대상 모드에요
Okay.
네
So next, this is some standard stuff that you've done a few times now to log in to Hugging Face.
다음은 여러분이 이미 몇 번 했던 기본 기능이에요 페이스 포옹에 로그인하기 위해서요
Um, and I've got the usual blurb that if you don't have hugging face account, but of course you have
포옹 얼굴 계정이 없으면 이런 문구가 뜨겠지만 지금쯤은
a hugging face account by now.
당연히 있겠죠
Uh, but you log in there, it's free, you get a token, and then you go to this section in the Colab,
로그인하면 무료고 토큰을 받아요 그리고 Colab에 있는
the, the key, and you use that to put in your, uh, your, your token, um, as you've done in the
이 구역으로 가서 키를 입력하고 토큰을 입력하면 돼요 전에도 해 봤잖아요
past.
그렇게 하면 이 셀을 실행할 수 있어요 얼굴 안기로 로그인되죠
Uh, the alternative is you could just type in your token there.
대안은 그냥 토큰을 입력하는 거죠
If you have any problems with accessing the notebook.
공책 접근에 문제가 있다면요
Okay, so without further ado, I am going to read in the base model without any quantization.
좋아요, 지체 없이 기본 모델에서 읽겠습니다 양자화 없이요
No funny business.
허튼짓하지 말고요
We're just going to read in the entire llama 3.18 billion base model, remembering that is the smallest
전체 라마를 읽어볼게요 180억 기본 모델이죠 라마 시리즈
of the llama series.
중 가장 작아요
Uh, device map equals auto means use a GPU if you've got one which which this box does.
장치 맵은 자동이란 뜻입니다 이 박스와 같은 GPU를 사용하라는 거죠
And I'm not going to run this now because I just ran it and it took about five minutes.
지금 실행하진 않겠습니다 방금 실행했는데 5분 정도 걸렸거든요
Uh, and it came up with a warning that it couldn't fit it all in GPUs.
GPU에 다 넣을 수 없다는 경고가 떴어요
So some of it went on the CPU.
그래서 일부는 CPU로 갔죠
And that's why if you look at the resources over on the right, you'll see that my GPU is 11 out of
오른쪽 리소스를 보시면 GPU 15기가 중 11기가가
15 gigs are filled up, and almost 13 gigs of Ram are also filled up.
차 있는 걸 보실 수 있습니다 거의 13기가 램도 차 있고요
So it's really taken up both the reason for the spike here is because I did it once, and then I restarted
여기 스파이크가 있는 이유는 두 가지 다 해당합니다 한 번 하고 다시 시작했거든요
Uh, obviously all you will see is the the one rise up to the top when you run this.
이걸 실행하면 제일 위에 있는 것만 보일 거예요
Okay.
네
And so now I'm going to print how much memory is this base model using up.
이제 이 기본 모델이 얼마나 많은 메모리를 사용하는지 프린트할게요
And again if you if you wanted to train this it would it would take many many more times.
다시 말하지만 훈련하려면 훨씬 더 많이 해야 해요
This this is just how much memory is the base model using up, and its memory footprint is just north
이건 기본 모델이 얼마나 많은 메모리를 사용하는지 보여줍니다 메모리 공간은
of 32GB, 32GB of memory being used.
32GB 북쪽 32GB 메모리가 사용되고 있어요
And you may remember that's what we said earlier.
아까 했던 말 기억하시죠?
It's basically 32 bit floats for each of the 8 billion parameters.
80억 매개 변수에 대한 32 비트 플로트죠
Okay.
네
So that's, uh, it's big.
정말 큰 변화죠
Uh, and let's just look at it.
어디 한번 볼까요?
You can just take a look by printing the base model itself.
기본 모델 자체를 프린트해서 살펴볼 수 있어요
And this now is a view on what it looks like, um, so briefly before, but we'll just pause for a moment.
지금 보시는 건 어떻게 생겼는지에 대한 건데요 아주 간략하지만 잠시 멈춰보죠
And again, this isn't going to be a deeply theoretical class, so I'm not going to do too much in the
다시 말씀드리지만 이론만 따지는 수업이 아니므로 제가 길게 설명하지
way of explaining this other than saying what you can.
않고 있는 그대로 말씀드릴게요
What is made clear when you look at the architecture of this neural network is that there are it consists
이 신경망 구조를 보면 명확히 알 수 있는 건 내장
of, first of all, an embedding layer, which is the thing that that takes text and turns it into it,
레이어로 구성돼 있다는 겁니다 텍스트를 취해 변환해
embeds it into vectors in the in the neural network.
신경망 내 벡터에 내장하는 거죠
So this is very it's like the, the encoder encoding LMS that we talked about before.
이건 아주∙∙∙ 아까 얘기했던 인코딩 LMS 같은 거죠
The first layer is embedding tokens, um, into a, um, a vector.
첫 번째 레이어는 토큰을 벡터로 넣는 거예요
Uh, and in fact, that is the dimensionality of how many possible tokens we have.
사실, 가능한 기념품이 얼마나 많은지 그게 차원이에요
And this is the dimensionality of the embedded vectors.
이건 내부 벡터의 입체성이에요
So there are then 32 layers called Lama decoder layers.
라마 디코더라는 층이 32개 있어요
32 sets of them.
32세트요
And each of those 32 looks like all of this.
32개 모두 이런 모양이에요
Let's get that right to there.
Get it을 하죠
Um, and so you can you can go through this, but you can see that it consists of the the set of attention
이 부분을 살펴보면 주의력 레이어 세트로 구성된 걸 볼 수 있어요 q, proj,
layers, which are called q, proj, k proj, v and o proj.
k proj, v, o proj라고 하죠
And these these are the layers that we have targeted in our target modules, which is typically what
이건 대상 모듈에서 우리가 대상으로 하는 층입니다 여러분이 주로 하는 거죠
you do.
다른 방법도 있지만 이게 가장 일반적인 방법이에요
And you'll see that, uh, some of these layers have 4000 odd dimensions in and out.
어떤 층은 4천여 개의 차원이 들락날락해요
Uh, this one and this one and some of them are 4000 in and and 1000 out.
이것과 이것, 어떤 건 4천 개, 1천 개예요
So they've got some different dimensionality there.
그래서 입체감이 좀 달라요
And that will be somewhat relevant when we look at the lora A and Lora B.
로라 A와 로라 B를 볼 때 어느 정도 관련이 있죠
But I'm not going to get too deep into this, but this is yours to experiment with and read up on if
너무 깊이 들어가진 않겠지만 여러분이 실험하고 읽어보세요 더 많은 정보가 필요하다면요
you want more more information about it.
get it get it
There is then a multi-layer perceptron layer with something that, for example, the the up is something
다중 인터셉트론 레이어도 있는데 예를 들어 위는 차원의 개수를 폭발적으로
that explodes out the number of dimensions, and then the down then reduces down the number of dimensions.
늘리고 아래는 차원의 개수를 줄이는 거죠
And that's followed by an activation function.
그리고 활성화 함수가 뒤따르죠
Again, for people that are more familiar with this stuff.
이런 것에 익숙한 분들을 위해서요
The activation function that's used for Lama is Selu, which you can see in the PyTorch documentation.
라마에 사용되는 활성화 함수는 셀루예요 피토크 문서화에서 보실 수 있죠
You can look at it and learn more about what that is and and why it is used.
그걸 보면 그게 무엇이고 왜 사용되는지 더 알 수 있죠
Um, so that is then followed by by layer norm layers.
그 뒤에 레이어 보통 레이어가 있어요
Um, and then at the very end there is a linear layer, the LM head.
그리고 맨 끝에는 LM 헤드라는 직선 층이 있어요
And this is sometimes targeted.
특정 목표를 노리기도 하죠
This is sometimes added to target modules.
대상 모듈에 추가되기도 하죠
As I mentioned before, in the cases where you wanted to generate something, where part of what you
전에 말씀드렸듯이 뭔가를 생성하고자 하는 경우 결과를 생성하는
want it to learn is to generate results, that will take a different format of some sort.
걸 배우길 원하는 경우 그건 일종의 다른 포맷을 갖죠
Maybe you want a particular structure of JSON, or maybe something completely different, like you want
JSON의 특정 구조를 원할 수도 있고 완전히 다른 걸 원할 수도 있죠 다른
it to speak a different language, or you want it to to structure things in some, some very unique
언어를 사용하길 원하거나 아주 독특한 방식으로 구조를 원하거나요
Then you might target this in your target modules as well.
그럼 이것도 대상 모듈에 대상으로 할 수 있죠
Um, but that gives you a sense of the architecture.
그러면 건축물이 어떤 느낌인지 알 수 있죠
And in a second, when we look at the Lora adapters, you'll see why I've taken a moment to dwell on
잠시 후 로라 어댑터를 보면 제가 왜 이 얘기를 계속하는지 알게 될
this.
거예요
All right.
좋아요
So we used up 32GB.
32GB를 썼어요
The next thing we need to do is to restart this session by going to runtime and restart session to clear
다음으로 할 일은 이 세션을 다시 시작하는 겁니다 런타임으로 가서요 세션을 다시 시작해 메모리를
out the memory so we can keep going.
지우고 계속 진행해야죠
There are some torch commands that will clear the cache, but in fact they're not aggressive enough.
캐시를 비우라는 명령이 있었지만 그렇게 적극적이지 않았어요
It still holds on to too much because we've consumed so much.
너무 많이 소비해서 아직도 너무 오래 붙어 있어요
The only way forwards now is to restart the session.
이제 유일한 방법은 세션을 다시 시작하는 거예요
So that's what I'll do.
그렇게 할 거예요
And I will see you in the next video once I have restarted and I'm back here again.
다음 비디오에서 다시 시작하면 다시 여기로 돌아오죠